Guide to the Alfred J. Kahn Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Alfred J. Kahn Papers,
1920-2009
Kahn, Alfred J., 1919-2009
11.76 linear ft. (28 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book & Manuscript Library Butler Library, 6th Fl. East, 535 West 114th St., New York, NY. 10027
MS#1549
8386417
This collection consists of papers relating to the personal life, military service, and academic career of Columbia University professor Alfred J. Kahn.
Biographical Note
Alfred J. Kahn was a pioneer in the field of social work and served as a member of the Columbia University faculty for fifty-seven years. Born in Williamsburg, Brooklyn, in 1919, Kahn spent much of his early life in the Bensonhurst neighborhood. His parents, Meyer and Sophie Kahn, raised their children in the Jewish faith. Kahn remained interested in his Jewish heritage through his college years, enrolling concurrently in the secular City College and in the Jewish Theological Seminary and graduating from both programs by 1940.
Kahn's interest in social work as a field of study developed during his college years. At City College, Kahn became active in the Zionist student organization called Avukah. As a student leader of Avukah, Kahn organized a national survey of Jewish college students in an effort to understand the particular needs and challenges of that community. This experience, along with a few courses in social work, convinced Kahn that this would be his vocation. After an initial rejection, Kahn was accepted into the M.S. program at the New York School of Social Work in 1941. He also remained engaged with the Jewish community through an administrative role in Avukah and a post as a Hebrew Sunday school teacher.
Kahn studied at the School of Social Work until 1942, when he entered the military. Stationed at the Air Force Drew Field Mental Health Unit in Florida-the first unit of its kind in the United States military-Kahn screened incoming patients and observed their patterns of adjustment and maladjustment. He also provided informal advice to soldiers (and occasionally their wives) through a column entitled "What's Your Problem?" Ultimately, he published a scholarly article based on his experiences at Drew and collected material that would help to launch his early career.
Upon his discharge from the military at the end of World War II, Kahn completed his M.S. at the New York School of Social Work and began his doctoral studies at Columbia University. He would maintain an affiliation with Columbia for the rest of his life. Kahn received the first doctorate in social work to be conferred at Columbia and, indeed, in the state of New York. He remained at Columbia, helping to develop the doctoral program and to shape the academic field of social work, particularly in the areas of family and child welfare, social service planning, and comparative international analysis.
In addition to his work as a professor, Alfred Kahn served as a consultant for federal, state, and local agencies as well as philanthropic organizations, in the development of social policy. His work in this capacity began very early in his career at the Citizen's Committee for Children (CCC). Kahn contributed to the CCC from 1948 to 1972, publishing a number of major studies on juvenile justice under CCC auspices. These publications drew Kahn onto the national stage in the 1950s as an expert on juvenile delinquency. He continued to serve as a policy advisor through the 1960s and 1970s, contributing to the shaping of Lyndon Johnson's Great Society programs.
Kahn remained interested in children and family structure throughout his long career. Over time, the geographic scope of his interest expanded. Along with his frequent collaborator Sheila Kamerman, Kahn embarked on comparative studies of European and American families and social policies. This research provided the basis for Kahn's increasingly frequent critiques of United States policies in the late 1970s and 1980s, and his advocacy for European-style socialized services to aid underprivileged Americans. At Columbia, Kahn and Kamerman established and co-chaired the Cross-National Studies research program, promoting comparative international scholarship.
Alfred Kahn received numerous honors and awards throughout his career and received several honorary degrees. Kahn retired in 1989 and continued to teach as a Professor Emeritus until 2004. He died in 2009, survived by his daughter, Nancy.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of a range of materials, relating primarily to Alfred Kahn's education, military service, and professional life. The materials include lesson plans and drafts, publications, reviews, research notes, conference proceedings, and correspondence. There is also one box of digital video tapes, probably documenting some of Kahn's lectures at Columbia. In addition, the collection includes a small amount of personal correspondence and several photographs
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series.
Series I: Personal, 1920-2009
Series II: Professional, 1942-2008
Series III: Audiovisual Material, 1977-2004
Subjects
Avukah, American Student Zionist Organization.; Citizens' Committee for Children of New York City.; Columbia University.--School of Social Work.; Columbia University.--School of Social Work.--Cross-National Studies Research Program.; Jewish Board of Guardians.; Kahn, Alfred J., 1919-2009.; Kamerman, Sheila B.; Child welfare--Government policy--New York.; Child welfare--Government policy--United States.; Conference proceedings.; Congressional committee records.; Family policy--United States.; Judaism and social problems--United States.; Juvenile delinquency--New York (State)--New York.; Juvenile delinquency--United States.; Social work education.; Social policy--United States.; Social policy--New York.; Soldiers--Mental health--United States.; Clippings (information artifacts); Military records.; Syllabi.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Files concerning consultations are restricted. Please see container list for exact box and folder.
Acquisition
Nancy V. Kahn, Gift 2010
- Series I: Personal, 1920-2009
  This series contains mixed materials relating to the family life, education, and military service of Alfred J. Kahn. The subjects covered include awards and honors, including honorary degrees. There are also personal records from Kahn's college and graduate career, including early statements of his interest in social work and documentation of his participation in the Avukah Zionist student organization. There are also materials pertaining to Kahn's family life, several photographs, and transcripts of eulogies from Kahn's memorial services in 2009.
  The series also documents Kahn's military service at the Air Force Drew Field Mental Health Unit during World War II. The Drew MHU, in Florida, was the first of its kind, and the material included from this period of Kahn's life provides insight into the early diagnosis and treatment of mental illness among soldiers. Kahn began research at Drew that contributed directly to his professional development and, as a result, some of the materials in this section are of a professional as well as a personal nature. One folder of patient interview notes has been restricted due to the personal nature of its contents.
  - General, 1941-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Awards and Honors, 1967-2005, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 2 to 3)
  - Education
    - 1939-1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1946-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Family, undated, 1920-1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Memorial, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Military, 1942-1945
    - "What the Soldier Thinks," 1944 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Personal Records, 1942-1945, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 12 to 13)
    - Articles, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "What's Your Problem?," 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Drew MHU Study, 1944-1947 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Drew MHU Manual, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Drew MHU Consultations, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      [Restricted until 2050]
  - Avukah Manual, 1941 (Box 27)
- Series II: Professional, 1942-2008
  This series consists of materials documenting Alfred J. Kahn's career and professional activities. The content includes published writing as well as drafts, lecture notes, press clippings, and conference proceedings. Kahn's associations with non-academic organizations and his contributions to city, state, and federal policy are also documented here.
  The majority of materials in this series pertain to Kahn's teaching and research activities, as well as his professional publications. Syllabi and lecture notes provide insight into Kahn's teaching methods. The series also includes records of Kahn's televised lectures on CBS as part of a 1968 Columbia University public education initiative.
  Many of the publications that Kahn produced over the course of his career are also present in this series, either in draft or final form. The series also includes some of the raw material Kahn collected in the form of notes from his research trips to Europe with frequent collaborator Sheila Kamerman.
  In addition to teaching and research, Kahn contributed to public discourse about social policy in an advisory role. These include community organizations such as the Citizens' Committee for Children (CCC). The series features extensive records of CCC communications and publications, including some of the work that Kahn published under CCC auspices. The series also features records of Kahn's congressional testimony and his contributions to official reports and committees. One issue of note is juvenile delinquency, an early area of expertise for Alfred Kahn that initiated his involvement with federal policy in the 1950s.
  - General, 1953-2001, (3 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 6 to 8)
  - Biographies, undated, 1959-2008 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, 1953-1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Publication Lists, undated, 1953- 2004 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Resumes, undated, 1959-1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "Growth and Development of AICP and COS," 1942, (3 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 4 to 6)
  - Citizens' Committee on Children
    - General, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 7 to 8)
    - 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - 1951-1953 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Proposal to Judge John Warren Hill, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - 1954 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1955 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 1956 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - "Major CCC Documents 1956-1957," 1956-1957, (4 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 4 to 7)
    - 1957 January-April (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - 1957 May-December (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - "For Children in Trouble," 1957 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - "Major CCC Documents 1957-1958," 1957-1958, (3 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 2 to 4)
    - 1958 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 1959 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - "The Planning and Coordination of Services for Children and Youth in New York City," 1957 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - 1960 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - "When Children Must Be Committed," 1960 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - 1961 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - 1962 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - "New York City Schools and Children Who Need Help," 1962 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - 1963 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 1964 January-February (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - 1964 March December (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - "Creating an Informed Community Presence," 1964, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 4 to 5)
    - 1965-1967 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - 1968-1970 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Basic CCC Documents, 1953-1956 (Box 27)
  - Conferences and Lectures, undated, 1945-2004
    - General, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - 1945-1946 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - 1947 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - 1948 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - 1949-1952 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 1955-1959 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - "Social Science Theory and Social Work Research," 1959 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 1960 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - "Panel Meeting on the Development of New Approaches to Community Mental Health Services," 1962, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 8 to 9)
    - 1963 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 1964 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - "Key Services for Unmarried Mothers," 1964 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Institute for Training in Community Psychiatry, 1964, (3 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 4 to 6)
    - 1965 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - "Daycare as a Social Instrument," 1965, (3 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 8 to 10)
    - 1966 January-August (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - 1966 September-December (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - 1967 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - "After Fifty Years" Minnesota School of Social Work, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - 1968 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - 1969 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - "Income Maintenance Alternatives," 1969 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - La Programmazione Sociale, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - 1970 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - 1973 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - 1974-1976 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - 1977 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - "Cleveland's Human Services," 1977 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Conference on Family Policy Proceedings, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Family Policy Conference, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - 1980 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - 1981 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - "The 80's: A New Decade For Social Work," 1982 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - 1984 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - 1985 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - 1986 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - 1989 January-May (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - 1989 June-December (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - 1992 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - 1995-1997 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - 1998 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - 1999 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - 2000-2004 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - "Towards An Australian Family Policy," 1980 (Box 28)
  - Correspondence
    - 1939-1959 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - 1960-1969 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - 1970-1979 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - 1980-1989 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - 1990-2006 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Jewish Board of Guardians
    - General, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - 1944-1946 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - 1947 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Press
    - General, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - 1950-1952 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - 1953 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - 1954, (3 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 10 to 12)
    - 1955-1959 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - 1960-1962 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - 1963 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - 1964 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - 1969 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - 1976 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - 1977 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - 1978 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - 1979 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - 1980 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - 1981 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - 1982 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - 1983 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - 1988 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - 1989 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - 1990-1994 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - 1995-2002 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Reports
    - 1940-1949 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - 1950-1954 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - 1955 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - "The Use of Dog Guides in the Rehabilitation of the Blind," 1956 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - 1956-1959 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - "New York City Boys Committed to State Training Schools in 1957 and 1958," 1959 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - New Jersey Youth Study Commission, 1960 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - 1960-1964 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - 1965 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - 1966 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - 1967-1969 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - "Development of Social Work Manpower and Knowledge in Relation to Critical Illness," 1968 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - "Social Planning in Pittsburgh," 1969 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - "Social Policy and the Distribution of Income," U.N. Report, 1969 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Interim Report to the Ford Foundation, 1970, (2 Folders) (Box 17, Folder 6 to 7)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - 1972, (2 Folders) (Box 17, Folder 9 to 10)
    - 1973-1975 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - "Social Services in New York City," 1973 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Task Force on "State of the Child," Report, 1974 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - 1976 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - 1977-1979 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - 1980-1982 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - 1985, (2 Folders) (Box 18, Folder 8 to 9)
    - "Tax Policies: How Do Families Fare?," 1985 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - "Mother-Only Families in Western Europe," 1987 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - 1988 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Federal Role In Child Care Hearing, September 22, 1988 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - 1989 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - "Hearings Before the Committee on Education and Labor," 1989 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - "Social Services for Children, Youth and Families in the U.S.," 1989 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - "Social Services for Children, Youth and Families: The New York City Study," 1990 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - 1990-2002 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - "Mental Health and Social Services," 1975 (Box 28)
  - Research, undated, 1946-2000
    - General (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - 1946 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - "A Program of Research in Juvenile Delinquency," 1956 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - 1959, (3 Folders) (Box 20, Folder 1 to 3)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Bound Interviews and Reports--Europe, 2000 March (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Europe, 1999 Summer (Box 28)
  - Teaching
    - General, undated (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - 1947-1950 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - 1951 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - 1952-1965 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - 1966, (2 Folders) (Box 20, Folder 11 to 12)
    - 1966 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - 1968, (3 Folders) (Box 21, Folder 3 to 5)
    - 1969 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - 1970-1976 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - 1979 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - 1980 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - 1983 Binder (Box 21, Folder 12)
    - 1983, (2 Folders) (Box 22, Folder 1 to 2)
    - 1983 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - 1984 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - 1985 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - 1986 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - 1987 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - 1990-1995 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - 1998-1999 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - 2000, (2 Folders) (Box 23, Folder 2 to 3)
    - 2001-2002 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - 2004 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Writings
    - "Miscellaneous Reprints or Unpublished Papers," 1944- 1995, (3 Folders) (Box 23, Folder 6 to 8)
    - 1938-1944 (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - 1945-1949 (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - "The Psychopath in the Armed Forces," 1946 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - 1950 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - 1951-1953 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - 1956-1959 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - 1962-1964 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - 1967-1969 (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - 1970-1972 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - 1975-1977 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - "European Family Policy Currents"--Draft, 1976 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - "Government and Family in the U.S."--Draft, 1977 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - "Government Structure Versus Family Policy"--Draft, 1979 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - 1980-1982 (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - 1985-1989 (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - "Contracting for Child & Family Services," 1999 (Box 25, Folder 11)
    - 1990-2008 (Box 25, Folder 12)
- Series III: Audiovisual Material, 1977-2004
  This Series consists of digital videotapes, labeled "8801 2004" and a number of audiotapes. The videotapes most likely document Kahn's lectures from Columbia University course 8801, "Comparative Histories of Social Welfare and Social Work," during his last year of teaching. The audiotapes contain a number of taped lectures. At the time of processing, these tapes had not been reviewed by RBML staff.
  - Videotapes
    - "Comparative Histories of Social Welfare and Social Work," 2004, (52 videotapes) (Box 26)
    - "Necessary Lightness," 1993, (VHS tape) (Box 26)
  - Audio Cassettes
    - Perspectives on National Family Policy, undated (Box 29)
    - Conversations About Children: International Developments, 1977 (Box 29)
    - Center for Philadelphia Studies, Health and Human Services, 1981, (2 tapes) (Box 29)
    - CW Lecture, 1984 (Box 29)
    - Public Social Services, Philadelphia, 1988 (Box 29)
    - Child Care, 1996 (Box 29)
      (Tape is marked 3 of 4)
    - Child Welfare and Welfare Reform, 1998 (Box 29)
      (Tape is marked 1 of 3)
    - Cleveland Case Study, undated (Box 29)
      (Tape is marked 3 of 3)
    - Unmarked Tapes, (4 Tapes) (Box 29)